William Walden Rubey Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Walden Rubey Papers 1920-1974 1951-1971
MSS38471
Rubey, William Walden, 1989-1974
32,250 items
95 containers plus 1 oversize
38 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Geologist and educator. Correspondence, memoranda, manuscripts of articles, book reviews, speeches, reports, research notes, press releases, printed materials, maps, illustrations, and other papers pertaining primarily to Rubey's career with the United States Geological Survey, as consultant on geological projects, and as member of professional, scientific, and educational organizations.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Aldrich, Henry R. (Henry Ray), 1891- --Correspondence.; Hubbert, M. King (Marion King), 1903-1989--Correspondence.; Longwell, Chester R. (Chester Ray), 1887-1975--Correspondence.; Oriel, Steven S.--Correspondence.; Rubey, William Walden, 1898-1974.
Organizations
Geological Society of America. Committee on the War Effort.; Geological Survey (U.S.); Geological Survey (U.S.). Strategic Minerals Program.; Lunar Science Institute.; Project Mohole.
Subjects
Biosphere.; Earthquakes--Colorado--Denver Region.; Geological mapping--Middle West.; Geological mapping--West (U.S.); Geology--Middle West.; Geology--Nomenclature.; Geology--Societies, etc.; Geology--West (U.S.); Submarine geology.; Thrust faults (Geology); Vanadium.; World War, 1939-1945--Science.
Places
Earth (Planet)--Crust.; Earth (Planet)--Mantle.
Occupations
Educators.; Geologists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of William Walden Rubey, geologist and educator, were given to the Library in 1974 by Mrs. Susan M. Rubey. A small addition was received by bequest of the Rubey estate in 1976.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1898, Dec. 19 Born, Moberly, Mo.
1919, Nov. 27 Married Susan Elsie Manovill
1920 A.B., University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo.
1920 1960 Geologist, United States Geological Survey
1922 1924 Instructor of geology, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1950 1951 Director, American Geological Institute
1953 D.Sc., University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo.
1955 1956 Visiting professor of geology at California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, Calif., and Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
1960 1969 Professor of geology and geophysics, University of California, Los Angeles, Calif.
1960 1974 Member, National Science Board
1974 Died, Los Angeles, Calif.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Walden Rubey (1898-1974) span the years 1915-1974, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1951-1971. The collection primarily documents Rubey's career with the United States Geological Survey, his consultant work on various geological projects, and his activities as a member of professional, scientific and educational organizations. Also included are materials relating to Rubey's technical speeches and writings in the earth sciences field. The collection is divided into the following series: General Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, and Oversize.
The General Correspondence series, 1921-1974, primarily contains incoming and outgoing correspondence between Rubey and associates involved in the earth science fields. Much of the earlier correspondence relates to his work as a geologist for the United States Geological Survey and includes letters written and received while Rubey was performing geological field work in areas of the Midwest, Southwest, the northern Great Plains, and the northern Rocky Mountains. Later correspondence primarily pertains to his involvement with numerous scientific and educational associations and his interest in the research and writings of colleagues.
The Speeches and Writings series, 1923-1974, is mostly comprised of research notes, drafts, correspondence, final copies, printed versions, and other related materials pertaining to Rubey's articles, book reviews and introductions, speeches, and reports. Research notes in this series are highly technical and often contain complex mathematical and scientific formulations. The series features many of Rubey's ground-breaking articles, along with related correspondence, illustrative materials, and research notes. Included are materials pertaining to such seminal works as “The Geologic History of Sea Water,” “The Development of the Hydrosphere and Atmosphere,” and the controversial “Role of Fluid Pressure in the Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting.” Co-authored with M. King Hubbert, the latter article was the cause of much dissension in the geological field. Letters from colleagues in this file primarily pertain to the validity of Rubey and Hubbert's fluid pressure hypothesis. The authors' replies to published discussions and critiques of their theory are also found in this series.
The Subject File, 1915-1974, is comprised of correspondence, memoranda, reports, newspaper clippings, press releases, printed matter, geological maps, research notes, and other materials relating to Rubey's professional activities as a geologist. Although the series contains extensive files pertaining to projects Rubey conducted for the United States Geological Survey, complete documentation of his Survey career as a whole is lacking. Notable files include records documenting his work in standardizing the nomenclature and symbols used for defining carbonaceous and stratigraphic materials, several projects that took place in the western states, and various geological mapping projects. Other significant files relate to Rubey's work with the Survey's Strategic Minerals Program, in which he was charged with supervising surveys for vanadium, an important ore used by steel manufacturers during World War II as a steel hardener.
Also contained in the Subject File are correspondence, memoranda, and reports pertaining to Rubey's work as a member of many professional, educational, and scientific organizations. Included are correspondence, memoranda, and reports documenting his efforts in the Mohole project, a joint effort in the 1960s between the National Science Foundation and the United States government to obtain a complete core record of the layers of the earth's crust and the upper part of the underlying mantle. The project was later discontinued by Congress due to dissension between scientists and government representatives over the administration of the project, congressional charges of political influence and irregularities in the awarding of the engineering contract, and other factors. Correspondence in this file contains Rubey's candid impressions of what he felt were the root causes of the project's failure.
Other significant files pertain to Rubey's role in establishing the Lunar Science Institute, his work as a member of the Geological Society of America's Committee on the War Effort, which made recommendations to the army on the strategic employment of geologists in the battlefield during World War II, and his efforts in conjunction with the United States Army Corps of Engineers to determine the cause of a series of earthquakes plaguing the Denver, Colorado, area.
Frequent correspondents include Henry R. Aldrich, M. King Hubbert, Chester R. Longwell, and Steven S. Oriel.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in four series:
General Correspondence, 1920-1974
Speeches and Writings, 1923-1974
Subject File, 1915-1974
Oversize, 1962-1966
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1920-1974 (Box 1-12)
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence with attachments between Rubey and friends, colleagues, and organizations.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent or organization and therein chronologically.
  - Abelson, Philip N., 1953-1962 (Box 1)
  - Altschuler, Z. S., 1959-1962, undated
  - Anderson, Charles A., 1942-1966
  - Armstrong, Frank, 1945-1965
  - “A” miscellaneous, 1939-1974, undated, (2 folders)
  - Ball, Max W., 1928-1950
  - Bateman, Alan M., 1925-1957
  - Behre, Charles H., Jr., 1929-1945, undated
  - Bell, A. H., 1928-1930
  - Berkner, Lloyd V., 1962-1973
  - Berry, Edward W., 1925-1944
  - Billings, Marland P., 1944-1949
  - Birch, Francis, 1939-1973
  - Boardman, Leona, 1928-1946
  - Bradley, Wilmot H., 1924-1973
  - Bowen, Norman L., 1938-1953
  - Bramlette, Milton N., 1924-1969, undated
  - Branson, E. B., 1926-1939
  - Bronk, Detlev W., 1948-1963
  - Bryan, Kirk, 1926-1949
  - Bucher, Walter H., 1928-1968, (2 folders)
  - Buddington, A. F., 1949-1960
  - Byerly, Perry, 1943-1968 (Box 2)
  - “B” miscellaneous, 1926-1974, (8 folders)
  - Cairns, Robert W., 1964
  - Campbell, Ian, 1951-1969
  - Cannon, Ralph S., 1949-1968
  - Chamberlin, Rollin T., 1934-1945
  - Cloos, Ernst, 1944-1962
  - Cloud, Preston E., 1951-1973, undated
  - Cobban, William, 1947, 1959
  - Cornell, S. D., 1954-1956
  - Cottam, Clarence, 1967
  - Creagh, Agnes, 1959-1963
  - Crosby, Gary W., 1967-1971
  - Crosby, Irving B., 1935-1941
  - Crowell, John, 1961-1973
  - Curtis, Winterton C., 1931-1963
  - “C” miscellaneous, 1925-1973, (4 folders)
  - Davis, Gregory, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Denison, Rodger A., 1943-1957
  - DeWolf, Frank W., 1921-1942
  - Dille, Glenn S., 1929-1930
  - Dobbin, C.E., 1930-1935
  - Dodge, Homer L., 1944-1953
  - Dorr, John A., 1969-1974
  - Dott, Robert H., 1965-1973
  - Duncan, Robert, 1970-1971
  - “D” miscellaneous, 1921-1971, undated, (4 folders)
  - Eardley, A. J., 1936-1953
  - Emberson, Frances G., 1945
  - Ewing, Maurice, 1946-1974
  - “E” miscellaneous, 1932-1972, (2 folders)
  - Farrell, Agnes M., 1922-1926, (2 folders)
  - Faul, Henry, 1946-1961
  - Fenner, C. N., 1933-1934
  - Flint, Richard F., 1928-1960
  - Fox, Sidney W., 1956-1974
  - Fryxell, Fritiof M., 1951-1955
  - “F” miscellaneous, 1929-1970, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Gardner, Louis S., 1938-1949
  - Garrels, Robert M., 1950-1968
  - Gault, Richard H., 1947-1960
  - Getting, Ivan A., 1971
  - Gilluly, James, 1929-1973
  - Glock, Waldo S., 1925-1946
  - Graham, Clarence H., 1957-1960
  - Green, Burdett, 1953-1968
  - Green, Harry W., 1967-1969
  - Griggs, David T., 1933-1973, (3 folders)
  - “G” miscellaneous, 1928-1973, (7 folders)
  - Hale, Lyle A., 1954-1960
  - Hamilton, Warren, 1960-1967
  - Heald, Kenneth C., 1925-1962
  - Heard, Hugh, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
  - Hedbert, Hollis, 1936-1961
  - Heroy, William B., 1944-1958
  - Hess, Harry Hammond, 1939-1971, (2 folders)
  - Horberg, Leland, 1933-1953
  - Horton, Robert E., 1933-1935
  - Hubbert, King M., 1935-1974, (4 folders)
  - Hull, J. P. D., 1927-1950
  - Hunt, Charles B., 1930-1958
  - Hutchinson, Evelyn G., 1948-1971
  - “H-J” miscellaneous, 1920-1972, (8 folders)
  - Keller, Walter D., 1933-1966 (Box 6)
  - Kennedy, George, 1949-1970
  - Klopsteg, Paul E., 1952-1968
  - Knopf, Adolph, 1927-1951
  - Krauskopf, Konrad B., 1945-1953
  - Krumbein, William C., 1935-1958
  - Kuiper, Gerard P., 1951-1956
  - “K” miscellaneous, 1929-1974, (4 folders)
  - Lafon, Michel G., 1974
  - Lane, E. W., 1933-1953
  - Leighton, M. M., 1928-1971, (2 folders)
  - Leith, Andrew, 1956-1971
  - Leonard, Al, 1962-1962
  - Leopold, Luna B., 1951-1971
  - Leverett, Frank, 1923-1929
  - Levorser, Arville I., 1942-1947
  - Library of Congress, 1962-1966
  - Longwell, Chester R.
    - 1921-1942, (2 folders)
    - 1943-1973, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Love, David J., 1936-1955
  - Lovering, T. S., 1933-1951
  - “L” miscellaneous, 1924-1974, (3 folders)
  - McGookey, Donald P., 1959-1970
  - McKnight, Edwin T., 1928-1966
  - MacDonald, Gordon J., 1958-1967
  - Mackin, Joseph H., 1944-1969
  - Macy, A. J., 1924-1929
  - McKelvey, Vincent E., 1945-1972
  - Melton, Frank A., 1923-1948
  - Menard, Henry W., 1957-1963
  - Middlebush, Frederick A., 1953
  - Middleton, E. R., 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - Moore, Raymond C., 1921-1967
  - Moulton, Gail F., 1923-1944
  - “M” miscellaneous, 1926-1973, (6 folders)
  - Newell, Norman D., 1939-1949
  - Newhouse, Walter H., 1948-1949
  - Nolan, Thomas B., 1934-1974, undated
  - Nye, Selden S., 1945-1963
  - “N” miscellaneous, 1927-1969
  - Oriel, Steven S.
    - 1961-1965, (4 folders)
    - 1966-1971, (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - Osborn, Elburt F., 1965-1968
  - “O” miscellaneous, 1925-1972
  - Peck, Raymond E., 1939-1964
  - Pecora, William T., 1951-1971
  - Pettijohn, Francis F., 1952-1971
  - Pettersson, Hans, 1947-1954
  - Platt, Lucian B., 1956-1964
  - Potter, Paul Edwin, 1951-1959
  - Powers, Sidney, 1926-1927
  - Press, Frank, 1962-1973
  - Pye, Willard D., 1944-1945
  - “P” miscellaneous, 1934-1971, (3 folders)
  - Raleigh, Berry, 1961-1966, (2 folders)
  - Reed, Ralph D., 1929-1937
  - Revelle, Roger, 1948-1968
  - Robbins, William J., 1954-1963 (Box 10)
  - Robert, Walter O., 1963-1967
  - Robinove, Charles J., 1956-1957
  - Rodgers, John, 1939-1973, (3 folders)
  - Ronov, Alexander B., 1956-1973
  - Ruby, Glenn M., 1925-1944, 1970-1971
  - “R” miscellaneous, 1925-1973, (3 folders)
  - Savage, T. E., 1929-1930
  - Sharp, Robert P., 1941-1955
  - Slichter, Louis B., 1950-1966
  - Smith, Waldo E., 1947-1960
  - Spieker, Edmund M., 1928-1972, (2 folders)
  - Stedanoff, Alexander, 1923-1932
  - “Sai-She” miscellaneous, 1930-1974, (2 folders)
  - “Shep-Swi” miscellaneous, 1929-1974, (5 folders) (Box 11)
  - Taylor, S. Ross, 1968-1971
  - Thom, W. Taylor, 1923-1959
  - Tracey, Joshua I., 1953-1963
  - Trask, Parker D., 1928-1956
  - Tunell, George, 1948-1966
  - Turano, Rosalind D., 1960-1961, undated
  - Tuttle, Frank O., 1956-1958
  - Titensor, Sidney, 1927-1950
  - “T” miscellaneous, 1924-1973
  - Urey, Harold C., 1950-1973
  - “U-V” miscellaneous, 1926-1972, (2 folders)
  - Voight, Berry, 1973-1974
  - Waters, Aaron C., 1946-1965, undated (Box 12)
  - Weaver, Charles E., 1939-1949
  - White, Lynn, Jr., 1958-1962
  - Wentworth, Chester K., 1928-1959, undated
  - Weller, Marvin J., 1928-1955, undated, (2 folders)
  - Wetherill, George W., 1959-1967
  - Whipple, Fred L., 1949-1950
  - Wilkinson, Cecil J., 1934-1952
  - Williams, James S., 1920-1955, undated
  - Wilmot, Sydney, 1937-1938
  - Wilson, John Tuzo, 1953-1971
  - Woodford, Alfred O., 1932-1955
  - “W” miscellaneous, 1927-1974, (4 folders)
  - Yen, John T., 1946-1965
  - “Y-Z” miscellaneous, 1923-1956, (2 folders)
- Speeches and Writings, 1923-1974 (Box 13-37)
  Manuscripts in various stages of preparation, including notes, correspondence, illustrative materials, drafts, final copies, and printed versions of articles, book reviews, book introductions, miscellaneous writings, critiques of manuscripts written by colleagues, reports, and speeches.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Articles (Box 13)
    - 1926, “Determination and the Use of Thicknesses of Incompetent Beds in Oil Field Mapping and General Structural Studies,” Economic Geology
    - 1927, “The Effect of Gravitational Compaction on the Structure of Sedimentary Rocks: A Discussion,” Bulletin of the American Association of Petroleum Geologists
    - 1928, “Gullies in the Great Plains Formed by Sinking of the Ground,” American Journal of Science
    - 1929, “Origin of the Siliceous Mowry Shale of the Black Hills Region,” Shorter Contributions to General Geology, United States Geological Survey
    - 1930
      - “Lithologic Studies of Fine-grained Upper Cretaceous Sedimentary Rocks of the Black Hills Region,” Shorter Contributions to General Geology, United States Geological Survey
      - “Shortening of Folded Strata and Scale of Structure Section”
        - Drafts
        - Research notes
          - Computations
          - Depth of folding
          - H and B structure
          - Laboratory model
          - Mechanics of rupture
          - Miscellaneous structure
    - 1933
      - “Equilibrium Conditions in Debris-laden Streams,” Transactions of the American Geophysical Union
      - “Settling Velocity of Gravel, Sands, and Silt Particles,” American Journal of Science
        - Correspondence and drafts, 1932-1933
        - Printed version
      - “The Size Distribution of Heavy Minerals within a Water-laid Sandstone”, Journal of Sedimentary Petrology
        - Correspondence and notes, 1932-1933
        - Drafts
        - Printed version
    - 1938 (Box 14)
      - “The Force Required to Move Particles on a Stream Bed,” Shorter Contributions to General Geology, United States Geological Survey For additional material see Container 34, 1935, Apr. 10
        - Printed version
        - Research notes
          - Coefficient of frictional resistance
          - General, (2 folders)
          - G. K. Gilbert's experiment, (2 folders)
          - Hydraulics, (3 folders)
          - Mean velocities
          - Settling velocities
          - Stream profiles
      - Discussion of “The Passage of Turbid Water through Lake Mead,” by N. C. Grover and G. S. Howard, American Society of Civil Engineers (Box 15)
    - 1951, “Geologic History of Sea Water: An Attempt to State the Problem,” Bulletin of the Geological Society of America
      - Correspondence
      - Illustrative materials, (2 folders)
      - Printed version
      - Requests for copies, 1951-1954, 1973, undated
      - Research notes
        - Abundance of gases
        - Area of continents and thickness of sediments
        - Average shale
        - CaCO2
          - CO2 equivalent
          - Deposition and saturation
          - Population and effect on CO2 equilibrium
          - River water added
        - CO2 vs. pH
          - 8̊, 15%
          - 30̊, 19.37%
          - CO2 equilibrium only
          - K1CaCO2, K1CaSO4
          - Original calculations (Box 16)
          - Saltwater, CaCO2, 8̊ 19.37%
        - Composition of earth's crust
        - Composition of Sandstone, Shale, Limestone
        - Deep sea sediments
          - General composition, (2 folders)
          - Glob ooze composition
          - Porosity and density, (2 folders)
          - Relative volume
        - Escape of gases
        - Escape velocity
        - Equilibrium constant
        - Excess volatiles
        - General, (3 folders) (Box 17)
        - Geochemistry
          - Calculations of a and c, Recent-Eocene
          - Deep sea and continental sediments, (2 folders)
          - Devonian-Permian
          - ∈-Silurian
          - Pre ∈-Silurian
          - Recent-Eocene
          - Recent-Eocene and general
          - Recent
          - T R-K (Box 18)
        - Geogram., 5%, C1
        - Isostatic considerations
        - Isostatics and differentials
        - Mean composition of continents and deep sea sediments
        - Na, SO3, C1, O2
        - Oceanic thermal gradients
        - Partial melting
        - pH of primitive oceans, (2 folders)
        - Pressure vs. depth
        - Spitzer equation
        - Thermal springs
        - Thickness
        - Water
    - 1955 (Box 19)
      - “The Development of the Hydrosphere and Atmosphere, with Special Reference to Probable Composition of the Early Atmosphere,” Crust of the Earth Symposium, Geological Society of America, special paper See also Container 35, 1954, Oct. 14
        - Correspondence, 1953-1955
        - Drafts, (4 folders)
        - Printed version
        - Research notes, 1954-1955
          - Atmosphere from cosmic abundance
          - Atmosphere from excess volatiles
        - Revision notes
      - “Early Structural History of the Overthrust Belt of Western Wyoming and Adjacent States,” Wyoming Geological Association Guidebook, 1952-1955
    - 1959
      - “Role of Fluid Pressure in Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting,” co-authored with M. King Hubbert, Bulletin of the Geological Society of America See also Container 37, 1957, Nov. 5
        - Corrections
        - Correspondence, 1957-1961, (6 folders)
        - Critiques and editing by colleagues, 1958 (Box 20)
        - Drafts, 1958, (6 folders)
        - Errata
        - Illustrative materials (Box 21)
        - Printed version
        - Requests for copies, 1959-1969, undated
        - Research notes
          - Abnormal pressure and rate of sedation
          - Diagrammatic structure sections
          - Fault thrusts
          - General, (3 folders) (Box 22)
          - Geologic rates in past, world maximum thickness
          - Gulf coast, (2 folders)
          - [K1/a3 vs. ∈]
          - p+/D, D and P
          - Permeability
            - Krumbein and Casagrande
            - Overthrust belt
          - Perry-porosity diagram, 1958-1959
          - Rates of deformation
          - Rates of geosynclinal sinking
          - Relative thickness of differential ages
          - Slide origins of thrusts
          - Terzaghi, Macey
          - Theory
      - “Role of Fluid Pressure in Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting: A Discussion by D. T. Griggs and C. B. Raleigh,” Bulletin of the Geological Society of America
      - “Role of Fluid Pressure in Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting: A Discussion by Walter L. Moore and Lymon C. Reese,” Bulletin of the Geological Society of America
    - 1960 (Box 23)
      - “Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting and the Development of Abnormal Fluid Pressure,” co-authored with G. T. Griggs and C. B. Raleigh
        - Correspondence, 1959-1960, (8 folders)
        - Draft
      - “Orogeny,” McGraw-Hill Encyclopedia, 1958-1960
      - “Role of Fluid Pressure in Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting: Reply to a Discussion by Hans P. Laubscher,” Bulletin of the Geological Society of America
        - Correspondence, 1959-1960
        - Drafts, (2 folders)
        - Printed version
    - 1961 (Box 24)
      - “Age of the Evanston Formation, Western Wyoming,” Wyoming Geological Association Guidebook and Short Papers in the Geologic and Hydrologic Sciences, United States Geologic Survey
      - “Diamictite Facies of the Wasatch Formation in the Fossil Basin, Southwestern Wyoming,” Short Papers in the Geologic and Hydrologic Sciences, United States Geological Survey
      - “Role of Fluid Pressure in Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting: Reply to Discussion by Francis Birch,” co-authored with M. King Hubbert, Bulletin of the Geological Society of America
      - “Role of Fluid Pressure in Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting: Reply to Discussion by Walter L. Moore,” co-authored with M. King Hubbert, Bulletin of the Geological Society of America
    - 1965, “Role of Fluid Pressure in Mechanics of Overthrust Faulting: Reply to Discussion by Gregory A. Davis,” co-authored with M. King Hubbert, Bulletin of the Geological Society of America, (3 folders)
    - 1966
      - “Orogeny,” McGraw-Hill Encyclopedia, 1966-1967
      - “Tectonic Implications of Gypsum Dehydration,” co-authored with Hugh C. Heard, Bulletin of the Geological Society of America
        - Correspondence, 1963-1965
        - Critiques and editing by colleagues, 1964-1965
        - Drafts, (3 folders)
        - Printed version
        - Requests for copies
        - Research notes
          - General
          - Gypsum and ophiolites
        - Revisions
    - 1968, “The Denver Earthquakes,” Science For additional material see Containers 45-47, Denver earthquakes (Box 25)
      - Award, Intersociety Committee for Rock Mechanics
      - Correspondence, 1967-1969
      - Drafts
      - Illustrative materials
      - Printed version
      - Research notes
        - Bleed off period
        - CO2 and photosynthesis
        - Calculations
          - General
          - Stress for pumping and gravity flow pressure
        - Carbon
        - Carbon cycle and brucite deposition
        - Daily earthquake magnitudes
        - Depth to static head
        - Derby earthquakes
        - General
        - Hoover, Donald
        - Magnitude frequency
        - Occluded gases and volcanic fumaroles (Box 26)
        - Period F, second shutdown
        - Permeability and time lag